

Alejandro Sánchez Peralta Head of Department

octubre 2022



National Institute of Statistics and Geography



+52 55 2758 0678



sanchez.alexito@gmail.com



san_alehandro



sanalexito

in

sanchez-peralta-alejandro

About me -

Data scientist with experience of more than five years in the information procesing and survey analisys for the INEGI. Among other functions, I am in charge of generating the official information at the country level of the ENVE, the ENCRIGE and the ENCIG. I have knowledge in statistics and fluency in managing, cleaning, analyzing and visualizing data using R, Python and Power BI tools. I like to address the generation of value from raw data.

WORK EXPERIENCE

INEGI

Head of Department, 2016 - To date.

- Data cleaning, preparation and validation for the correct generation of survey KPIs (ENVE, ENCRIGE and ENCIG) using data wrangling libraries such as Tidyverse, Dplyr, Stringr in R; or Pandas when the use of Python is required.
- Collaboration with data engineers and other data scientists for the implementation of models that support decision-making based on quantitative evidence. This includes the design of dashboards with Shyni or Power BI and the generation of tabulations in Excel.
- Integration of the documentation of the validation process of the information streams of different surveys, as well as the generation of technical reports through Markdown and Google Colaboratory.
- Key achievements in my actual role include redesigning computational processes department-wide to improve efficiency in 30%. I also been able to improve production quality, through implementation of text analysis, which reduced delivery times by 25%.

INEGI

Jr Data Analyst, 2015 - 2016.

- Review and data contrast in executive presentations on issues of public safety, victimization and law enforcement.
- Elaboration of forecasts for different public security indicators such as total crimes or the "dark number of crimes" using the Forecast library.
- Calculation of different indicators for the National Government Surveys using the Survey library of R.

UAM-I

Associate Professor, 2010 - 2015.

 Quarterly class planning. Organization of workshops and consultancies to complement the academic training of students. In this position, in addition to teaching, I have been part of the organizing committee of the XXI and XXII Week of Mathematics, which takes place annually in the Mathematics Department of UAM-Iztapalapa.

Education

- Power BI Data Analysis and Business Intelligence, 2022, Ûdemy (21 hours.
- Results Based Budgeting Diplomate, 2022. SHCP (120 hours)
- Master of Mathematics, 2010, Universidad Autónoma Metropolitana-Iztapalapa.
- Bachelor of Mathematics, 2007, Universidad Autónoma Metropolitana-Iztapalapa.

Publications

 mainblueFinal Offer Arbitration. Determination of the optimal payment in an environmental dispute, Reality, Data and Space. International Journal of Statistics and Geography, Vol.8, No.3, pp.15-29, 2017.,

Extracurricular activities

• Transparency Innovation Contest 2021.

Participation in the "First Dataton on the Platform Your City, Your Money" organized by the Digital Agency for Public Innovation (ADIP) with the Income Analysis Project of the Mexico City Metro.

